Guide to the Mothers of World War Veterans records 1917-1958
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Mothers of World War Veterans records
1917-1958
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7534 Email: cpnws@wwu.edu
XOE_CPNWS0287MothersClub
Mothers of World War Veterans
.5 linear feet
The Mothers of World War Veterans records contain meeting minutes, correspondence, newspaper clippings, etc. documenting the activities of a women's club in Bellingham, Washington from 1917 through 1958.
Founded November 10, 1917 in Bellingham Washington as an auxiliary to the National League for Woman's Service, the club was first called the Mothers Club of Men in Service. Objectives were to maintain true allegiance to the government of the United States, to inculcate lessons in patriotism and love of country among children and in the community and encourage the spread of universal liberty and equal rights for all. (Source: Bellingham Herald, "World War I Mothers' Club members dwindle," 1971 May 30.)
Through the years the club had a number of names, including Mother of Men in Service (1917-1919), American Mothers of World War Veterans (1919-1920), Mothers of World War Veterans (1920-post WWII?), Mothers Club of the World War Veterans No. 1 and Mothers of World War Veterans (1956-1958).
The club initiated the foundation of Bellingham’s Memorial Park, and also raised money to donate the trees and plaques commemorating soldiers lost in World War I. During World War II members of the group were active volunteers with the Red Cross. The club continued to meet weekly even in times of peace because of the close friendships that they held. Members would sometimes even meeting in the homes of women who could not venture outside. The Mothers of World War Veterans disbanded in 1958.
The Mothers of World War Veterans records cover the years 1917 through 1958. The records include a members list and history, meeting minutes, correspondence and newspaper clippings. The members list not only contains names of the charter members and others, and also lists all club presidents. Minutes include articles of formation, lists of mothers and their sons, and the constitution and bylaws of the group. They also contain newspaper clippings, letters and other materials describing the creation of and planting of trees in Memorial Park in Bellingham, Washington, as well as members' volunteer involvement during World War II. Later minutes describe the decline of the club. Correspondence includes two thank-you letters and three 25th anniversary cards. The collection contains two newspaper clippings: one discussing the Bellingham Memorial Park tree plaques in 1966, and the other commemorating the last two living club members in 1971.
The collection is open to the public.
Donated by Christine J. Cameron of the American Legion Auxiliary League on April 30, 2008.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Mothers of World War Veterans--Archives
Bellingham (Wash.)--History
Women--Washington (State)--Bellingham--Societies and Clubs--History--Sources; World War, 1914-1918--Women--Washington (State)--Bellingham; World War, 1939-1945--Women--Washington (State)--Bellingham
Women--Bellingham--Washington (State)
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Members, undated (Box-folder 1/1)
- Minutes, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Minutes, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Minutes, 1919-1925 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Minutes, 1925-1933 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Minutes, 1933-1940 (Box-folder 1/6)
- Minutes, 1940-1945 (Box-folder 1/7)
- Minutes, 1953-1958 (Box-folder 1/8)
- Correspondence, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 1/9)
- Newspaper clippings, 1966; 1971 (Box-folder 1/10)